Guide to the George Eliot and George Henry Lewes Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
George Eliot and George Henry Lewes collection
1834-1981
GEN MSS 963
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
14.3
(64 boxes)
The collection includes correspondence by, to and about Eliot and Lewes. There are 4 journals, 1 diary, several notebooks with notes for a projected novel, quotes, poetry, and early school essays all belonging to George Eliot, accompanied by reviews and scripts of dramatizations of Daniel Deronda in the 1920s and 1970s. With 3 journals, 9 diaries, and notebooks with research notes belonging to George Henry Lewes, accompanied by miscellaneous writings, including several chapters of Problems of Life and Mind. There is also printed material, reviews, memorabilia, and photograph portraits of Eliot and Lewes as well as artwork by others. Principal correspondents include members of the Lewes family, Caroline and Charles Bray, John Emerich Edward Dalberg Acton, Barbara Leigh Smith Bodichon, John Chapman, Anna Chalmers and J. W. Cross, Alexandre D'Albert-Durade, Frederic Harrison, Sara Sophia Hennell, Frances Lucy Evans Houghton, Maria Lewis, Edward Robert Bulwer Lytton, Herbert Spencer, and Anthony Trollope.
Eliot, George, 1819-1880
Lewes, George Henry, 1817-1878
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired by gift and purchase from various sources.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
After George Eliot's death there were four principal groups of her manuscripts and private papers held by the families of Evans, Blackwood, Lewes, and Cross. Her family letters were at Derby in the hands of her grandnieces, the Evans sisters. Her long correspondence about the publication of her books was in the Edinburgh office of William Blackwood and Sons, who have since deposited it in the National Library of Scotland. The Blackwoods also owned the manuscript of Scenes of Clerical Life, which was sold in 1911 to the Pierpont Morgan Library. The manuscripts of her other works George Eliot bequeathed with all her literary rights to Charles Lee Lewes, her residuary legatee and sole executor of her estate. In 1891 his widow presented these manuscripts (except for "Brother Jacob" and "A College Breakfast-Party"), bound in 24 volumes, to the British Museum. On June 27, 1923 her three daughters sold many of the remaining George Eliot papers at Sotheby's; they were widely dispersed.
Charles Lewes had lent George Eliot's letters and journals to John Walter Cross, who was writing George Eliot's Life (1885). Apparently believing that they belonged to him, Cross retained them. On his death in 1924 they passed to his niece Miss Elsie Druce, who during the 1930's disposed of most of them in several sales at Sotheby's. Through the zealous interest of Professor Chauncey Brewster Tinker, who had been appointed Keeper of Rare Books in 1930, many of them were purchased for Yale. In that year he secured the largest single group, consisting of 620 letters to the Brays and the Hennells, which with 46 early letters to Maria Lewis formed the nucleus of the Yale collection. In 1931 George Eliot's Commonplace Book and her most important Journal (1854-61) were also acquired, as well as her Diary for 1880, and the travel journals of her trips to Germany (1858), to Italy (1860 and 1864), and to Normandy (1865). From his own collection Mr. Tinker gave among other manuscripts George Eliot's Journal (1861-77). Yale thus has all the extant journals and diaries except the diary for 1879, which is in the Berg Collection at the New York Public Library.
From Lewes's last surviving granddaughter Mrs. E. Carrington Ouvry (1877-1974), Yale secured the manuscript of "Brother Jacob" bound with that of "A College Breakfast-Party", and George Eliot's translation of Spinoza's Ethics. Of the greatest value to scholars are all of Lewes's extant journals and diaries except that for 1878, of which there is a microfilm. The manuscripts of five of Lewes's plays are included in the collection. There are several notebooks used for his Biographical History of Philosophy and Goethe's Life, and for his work on physiology and psychology, as well as many fragments of his Problems of Life and Mind, of which George Eliot completed and published the final volume.
Autograph letters have been added continually since the collection began. In 1975 there were more than 1030 by George Eliot and 220 by G. H. Lewes. Of letters to and about them there were more than 1040. The earliest family letters, including the only known one to George Eliot's father, were purchased in 1969 from the widow of his great-great-grandson Robert Evans, and George Eliot's letters to John Walter Cross and his family were purchased from Miss Druce's heir, Mr. Ian Maclean, in 1970.
[above written by] Gordon S. Haight.
Authors, English -- 19th century -- Archives; Novelists, English -- 19th century -- Archives; Diaries; Photographic prints; Acton, John Emerich Edward Dalberg Acton, Baron, 1834-1902; Bodichon, Barbara Leigh Smith, 1827-1891; Bray, Charles, Mrs., 1814-1905; Bray, Charles, 1811-1884; Browning, Oscar, 1837-1923; Burne-Jones, Georgiana, Lady, 1840-1920; Chapman, John, 1822-1894; Cross, Anna Chalmers, 1813-1878; Cross, J. W. (John Walter), 1840-1924; D'Albert-Durade, Alexandre Louis Francois, 1804-1886; Eliot, George, 1819-1880; Harrison, Frederic, 1831-1923; Hennell, Sara S.; Houghton, Frances Lucy Evans, 1805-1882; Lewes, Charles Lee, 1843-1891; Lewes, Edgar James, d. 1836?; Lewes, George Henry, 1817-1878; Lewes, Herbert Arthur, 1846-1875; Lewes, Thornton; Lewis, Maria, 1800?-1887; Lytton, Edward Robert Bulwer Lytton, Earl of, 1831-1891; Spencer, Herbert, 1820-1903; Trollope, Anthony, 1815-1882; Lewes, Gertrude
- Section I. Letters by GEORGE ELIOT to:, 1877 Feb 13
  - Allingham, William, 1824-1839, 1877 Feb 13 (Box 1)
    - ----, 1877 May 21 (Box 1)
  - Amberley, Katharine Louisa (Stanley); Russell, viscountess, 1842-1874, 1868 Apr 29 (Box 1)
  - Barclay, Martha (Jackson); (Mrs. Henry Barclay), 1841 Mar? (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    LETTERS FROM A TOWN MOUSE TO A COUNTRY MOUSE
    General note
    Tinker 870
  - Belloc, Elizabeth [Bessie] Rayner (Parkes), 1829-1925 (Mme Louis Belloc), [1870] Dec 29 (Box 1)
  - Beneke, Miss, 1880 Mar 19 (Box 1)
  - Blackwood, John, 1818-1879, 1861 Mar 23
    - ----, 1869 May 11 (Box 1)
    - ----, 1878 Jan 26 (Box 1)
    - ----, 1878 Jul 30 (Box 1)
    - ----, 1879 Jan 13 (Box 1)
    - ----, 1879 Oct 6 (Box 1)
  - Blackwood, William, 1836-1912, 1868 Mar 15 (Box 1)
  - Bodichon, Barbara (Leigh Smith) 1827-1891 (Mme Eugène Bodichon), [1861 Sep 3] (Box 1)
  - Bond, Edward Augustus, 1815-1898, 1874 Mar 19 (Box 1)
  - Bowen, Charles Synge Christopher 1835-1894, 1872 Jan 18 (Box 1)
  - Bray, Charles & Bray, Caroline (Hennell); Bray, Charles, 1811-1884; Bray, Caroline (Hennell), 1814-1905., 1842-1880
    Unless otherwise indicated the letters are addressed to Mr. & Mrs. Bray. Several letters, as indicated, are also addressed to Miss Sara Sophia Hennell.
    - Mrs. Bray, [1842 Feb] (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1842 Mar 6] (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1842 Mar 12?] (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1842 Sep] (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1842 Dec] (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1842? Dec] (Box 1)
    - Wednesday Mrs. Bray, [1843 Nov 8] (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1843] Nov 20 (Box 1)
    - Friday Mrs. Bray, [1843 Nov 24] (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1843 Nov 30 (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1844 Jun 18] (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1845 May?] (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1845 May 25] (Box 1)
    - ----, [1846 Jun 1] (Box 1)
    - Wednesday Mrs. Bray, [1846 Oct 21] (Box 1)
      The "Bücherworm letter," published in the Gazette, July 1971]
    - ----, [1847] Oct 3 (Box 1)
    - ----, [1848] May 31 (Box 1)
    - Monday Mr. Bray, [1848 Jun 5] (Box 1)
    - The Brays, Sara & Charles C. Hennell, [1848] Jun 8 (Box 1)
    - Sunday Mr. Bray, [1848 Jun 11] (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1849 May] (Box 1)
    - Wednesday, [1849 May 30] (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1849] Jul 27 (Box 1)
    - The Brays & Miss Hennell, [1849] Aug 5 (Box 1)
    - The Brays & Miss Hennell, [1849] Aug 20 (Box 1)
    - ----, [1849] Aug 28 (Box 1)
    - ----, [1849] Sep 13 (Box 1)
    - ----, [1849] Sep 20 (Box 1)
    - ----, [1849] Oct 4 (Box 1)
    - ----, [1849 Oct 11] (Box 1)
    - ----, [1849 Oct 24] (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1849 Oct 26] (Box 1)
    - The Brays & Miss Hennell, [1849 Dec 4] (Box 1)
    - The Brays & Miss Hennell, [1849 Dec 22] (Box 1)
    - ----, 1850 Jan 28 (Box 1)
    - ----, [1850 Feb 15] (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1850] Mar 1 (Box 1)
    - Wednesday Mrs. Bray, [1850 Apr 24] (Box 1)
    - ----, [1850 Nov 30] (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1851 Jan 8] (Box 1)
    - ----, [1851 Feb 15] (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1851 Oct 4] (Box 1)
    - Wednesday Mr. Bray, [1851 Oct 8] (Box 1)
    - The Brays & Miss Hennell, [1851 Oct 22] (Box 1)
    - The Brays & Miss Hennell, 1851 Nov 21 (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1851] Nov 27 (Box 1)
    - Saturday Mrs. Bray, [1851 Dec 20] (Box 1)
    - Tuesday, [1851 Dec 23] (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1852] Jan 12 (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1852 Jan 23] (Box 1)
    - Friday Mr. Bray, [1852 Jan 30] (Box 1)
    - Monday The Brays & Miss Hennell, [1852 Feb 2] (Box 1)
    - Saturday Mrs. Bray, [1852 Feb 7] (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1852] Feb 16 (Box 1)
    - Saturday Mrs. Bray, [1852 Feb 28] (Box 1)
    - Monday Mr. Bray, [1852 Mar 8] (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1852 Mar 29] (Box 1)
    - Tuesday Mrs. Bray, [1852 Mar 30] (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1852] Apr 17 (Box 1)
    - Monday, [1852 Apr 26] (Box 1)
    - Tuesday, [1852 Apr 27] (Box 1)
    - Saturday The Brays & Miss Hennell, [1852 May 1] (Box 1)
    - Wednesday, [1852] May I5 (Box 1)
    - Thursday morning Mrs. Bray, [1852 May 13] (Box 1)
    - Monday Mr. Bray, [1852 May 17] (Box 1)
    - Monday, [1852 May 24] (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1852] May 27 (Box 1)
    - Wednesday The Brays & Miss Hennell, [1852 Jun 21] (Box 1)
    - Saturday, [1852 Jun 5] (Box 1)
    - Monday, [1852 Jun 14] (Box 1)
    - The Brays & Miss Hennell, 1852 Jun 21 (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1852] Jun 23 (Box 1)
    - Tuesday Mr. Bray, [1852 Jun 29] (Box 1)
    - Wednesday Mr. Bray, [1852 Jun 30] (Box 1)
    - Friday morning Mrs. Bray, [1852 Jul 2] (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1852 Jul 4] (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1852] Jul 13 (Box 1)
    - Wednesday Mr. Bray, [1852 Jul 14] (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, 1852 Jul 21 (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1852 Jul 29] (Box 1)
    - Thursday Mrs. Bray, [1852 Aug 12] (Box 1)
    - Saturday Mrs. Bray, [1852 Sep 11] (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1852 Sep 18] (Box 1)
    - Saturday The Brays & Miss Hennell, [1852 Oct 2] (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1852 Oct 2] (Box 1)
    - ----, 1852 Oct 7 (Box 1)
    - ----, 1852 Oct 12 (Box 1)
    - Thursday, [1852 Oct 21] (Box 1)
    - Saturday, [1852 Oct 24] (Box 1)
    - ----, [1852 Nov 6] (Box 1)
    - Thursday Mrs. Bray, [1852 Nov 11] (Box 1)
    - Saturday, [1852 Nov 13] (Box 1)
    - Monday, [1852 Nov 22] (Box 1)
    - ----, [1852 Dec 4] (Box 1)
    - Monday Mr. Bray, [1852 Dec 6] (Box 1)
    - Monday night Mr. Bray, [1852 Dec 6] (Box 1)
    - Friday night, [1852 Dec 10] (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1852 Dec 18] (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1852] Dec 21 (Box 1)
    - ----, [1852 Dec 25] (Box 1)
    - The Brays & Miss Hennell, [1852 Dec 31] (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1853 Jan 3] (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1853 Jan 8] (Box 1)
    - Saturday The Brays & Miss Hennell, [1853 Jan 15] (Box 1)
    - Monday morning Mr. Bray, [1853 Jan 17] (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1853 Jan 22] (Box 1)
    - Monday morning Mr. Bray, [1853 Jan 24] (Box 1)
    - Tuesday Mr. Bray, [1853 Jan 25] (Box 1)
    - ----, [1853 Jan 29] (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1853 Feb 15] (Box 1)
    - Saturday, [1853 Feb 19] (Box 1)
    - Saturday, [1853 Feb 26] (Box 1)
    - ----, 1853 Mar 5 (Box 1)
    - ----, [1853 Mar 12] (Box 1)
    - Friday Mr. Bray, [1853 Mar 18] (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1853 Mar 30] (Box 1)
    - ----, [1853 Apr 11] (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1853 Apr 16] (Box 1)
    - ----, [1853 Apr 30] (Box 1)
    - Monday, [1853 May 2] (Box 1)
    - ----, [1853 May 4] (Box 1)
    - Wednesday Mr. Bray, [1853 May 25] (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1853 May 30] (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1853 Jun 13] (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Bray & Miss Hennell, [1853 Jun 17] (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1853 Aug 3] (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1853] Aug 9 (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1853 Aug 12?] (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1853 Aug 21] (Box 1)
    - Saturday, [1853 Sep 17] (Box 1)
    - ----, [1853 Sep 19] (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1853 Oct 20] (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1853 Oct 29] (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1853] Nov 3 (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1853 Nov 5] (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1853 Nov 15] (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1853 Dec 2 (Box 1)
    - Friday morning Mr. Bray, [1853 Dec 9] (Box 1)
    - Thursday Mrs. Bray, [1853 Dec 29] (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, 1854 Jan 12 (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1854] Feb 6 (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, 1854 Mar 15 (Box 1)
    - Saturday Mrs. Bray, [1854] Apr 18 (Box 1)
    - Friday Mrs. Bray, [1854 May 19] (Box 1)
    - Saturday Mr. Bray, [1854 May 27] (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1854 Jun 6] (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1854 Jun 8] (Box 1)
    - Wednesday Mrs. Bray, [1854 Jun 28] (Box 1)
    - Monday Mrs. Bray, [1854 Jul 3] (Box 1)
    - Friday Mr. Bray, [1854 Jul 14] (Box 1)
    - Wednesday The Brays & Miss Hennell, [1854 Jul 19] (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1854 Nov 3] (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, 1855 May 1 (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, 1855 May 7 (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1855] Jun 23 (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1855] Sep 4 (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, 1855 Sep 13 (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1855 Oct] (Box 1)
    - Monday Mr. Bray, [1855 Oct 15] (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, 1855 Nov 21 (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, 1856 Jan 1 (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1856] Mar 26 (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, 1856 Mar 31 (Box 1)
    - Tuesday Mr. Bray, [1856 Apr 1] (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, 1856 Jun 6 (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, 1856 Aug 6 (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1856] Sep 1 (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1856] Sep 5 (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1856 Oct] (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1856] Nov 28 (Box 1)
    - Wednesday Mr. Bray, [1856 Dec 2] (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1856] Dec 29 (Box 1)
    - Saturday Mr. Bray, [1857 Jan] (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1857] Apr 5 (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1857 Jun 5 (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, 1857 Oct 30 (Box 1)
    - Friday Mrs. Bray, [1857 Oct 30] (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, 1857 Nov 15 (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, 1857 Dec 23 (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1858] Mar 25 (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1858 Mar 29] (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1858 Mar 29] (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1858] Mar 31 (Box 1)
    - Mr. Bray, [1858] Oct 13 (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1858 Nov 26 (Box 1)
    - Christmas Day Mr. Bray, [1858 Dec 25] (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1859] Feb 22 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1859] Feb 24 (Box 2)
    - ----, [1859] Feb 27 (Box 2)
    - ----, [i.e. 28] (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1859] Mar 8 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1859 Mar 11] (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1859 Mar 21] (Box 2)
    - Saturday evening Mr. Bray, [1859 Jun 18] (Box 2)
    - Mr. Bray On verso of letter, [1859 Jun 24] (Box 2)
    - from GHL to Mr. Bray Monday evening The Brays &, [1859 Jun 27] (Box 2)
    - Miss Hennell Mr. Bray, 1859 Jul 5 (Box 2)
    - Mr. Bray, 1859 Jul 23 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1859] Jul 26 (Box 2)
    - Mr. Bray, [1859] Aug 20 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1859] Aug 23 (Box 2)
    - Wednesday Mr. Bray, [1859 Sep 7] (Box 2)
    - Mr. Bray, 1859 Sep 18 (Box 2)
    - Mr. Bray, [1859 Sep 19] (Box 2)
    - Monday Mr. Bray, [1859 Sep 26] (Box 2)
    - Mr. Bray with postscript by GHL, [1859 Sep 28] (Box 2)
    - Mr. Bray, [1859 Sep 30] (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1859 Oct 3?] (Box 2)
    - Monday Mr. Bray, [1859 Nov 21?] (Box 2)
    - Mr. Bray, [1859] Nov 25 (Box 2)
    - Tuesday Mr. Bray, [1860 Jan 3] (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1860 Jul 10] (Box 2)
    - Mr. Bray, [1860] Jul 14 (Box 2)
    - Mr. Bray, 1860 Jul 18 (Box 2)
    - Mr. Bray, [1860 Jul 30] (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1860 Sep 11 (Box 2)
    - Tuesday evening Mrs. Bray, [1860 Sep 18] (Box 2)
    - Mr. Bray, [1861] Mar 19 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1861 Jul 8 (Box 2)
    - Mr. Bray, [1861] Jul 13 (Box 2)
    - Mr. Bray, 1861 Aug 21 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1862 Jan 13 (Box 2)
    - Thursday Mrs. Bray, [1862 Feb 6] (Box 2)
    - Saturday evening Mrs. Bray, [1862 May 10?] (Box 2)
    - Mr. Bray, 1862 Dec 29 (Box 2)
    - Mr. Bray, 1862 [i.e. 1863] (Box 2)
    - ---- Mrs. Bray, 1862 [i.e. 1863] (Box 2)
    - ---- Mrs. Bray, 1863 Jun 1 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray & Miss Hennell, 1863 Sep 1 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1863 Sep 27 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1863 Nov 14 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1863 Dec 4 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1863 Dec 26 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1864 Mar 7] (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1864 May 2 (Box 2)
    - Mr. Bray, 1864 Dec 15 (Box 2)
    - Mr. Bray, 1864 Dec 28 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1865 Mar 18 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1865] May 27 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1856 [i.e. 1865] (Box 2)
    - ---- (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1865] Nov 10 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1866 Jun 5 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1866 Dec 26 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1867 Mar 25 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1867 Apr 6 (Box 2)
    - Mr. Bray, [1867] Jul 12 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1867] Jul 16 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1867 Nov 10 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1867 Dec 7] (Box 2)
    - Tuesday morning Mrs. Bray, [1868 Mar 10] (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1868 May 7 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1868 Oct 11 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1868 Nov 30 (Box 2)
    - Mr. Bray, 1868 Dec 19 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1869 Jun 13 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1869?] Jul 11 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1869 Jul 22 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1869 Aug 21 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1869] Aug 23 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1869 Oct 20 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1871] Feb 27 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1871 Apr 3 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1871 Jul 25 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1871 Aug 3 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1871 Oct 6 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1872] Apr ]5 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1873 Mar 20 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1873 Mar 22 (Box 2)
    - Mr. Bray, 1873 Apr 14 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1873 Jun 2 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1873 Sep 2 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, [1873 Sep 11] (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1873 Oct 10 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1873 Dec 22 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1874 Feb 17 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1874 Mar 25 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1874 May 29 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1874 Nov 23 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1874 Nov 24 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1875 Jan 14 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1876 Feb 3 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1876 Dec 21 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1877 Mar 20 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1877 Nov 23 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1878 Jun 7 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1878 Jul 8 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1878 Jul 12 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1878 Aug 26 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Bray, 1880 Nov 28 (Box 2)
  - Brock, Mrs. (housekeeper at Witley), 1878 Jun 17 (Box 2)
  - Brookfield, Jane (Elton), 1821-1894 (Mrs. William Henry Brookfield), 1867 Dec 14 (Box 2)
  - Brown, Dr. George Dransfield, 1872 Dec 8 (Box 2)
  - Browning, Oscar, 1837-1923
    - ----, 1867 Jul 26 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1869 Jul 28 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1869 Oct 14 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1870 May 8 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1870 Oct 18 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1873 Mar 16 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1875 Mar 2 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1877 Feb 12 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1877 May 26 (Box 2)
  - Burne-Jones, Sir Edward Coley, 1833-1898
    - ----, 1873 Mar 20 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1877 May 8 (Box 2)
  - Burne-Jones, Georgiana (Macdonald), Lady, 1840-1920
    - ----, 1870 Jun 13 (Box 2)
    - ----, [1870 Jun 14] (Box 2)
    - ----, 1870 Jun 26 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1870 Jul 10 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1874 Aug 3 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1875 May 11 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1877 Apr 28 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1877 Dec 3 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1878 Mar 23 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1878 Aug 26 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1878 Nov 18 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1879 Jun 3 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1879 Jun 29 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1879 Aug 11 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1879 Oct 18 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1880 May 5 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1880 Sep 9 (Box 2)
  - Burton, Sir Frederic William, 1816-1900, 1870 Jul 6 (Box 2)
  - Cameron, Julia Margaret. (Box 2)
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: Section III, Parrish, M.L.
  - Cash, Mary (Sibree), 1824-1895, [1847] May 10
    - ----, [1851 Jan] (Box 2)
    - ----, 1857 Jun 6 (Box 2)
  - Chapman, John, 1821-1894
    - ----, 1851 Jun 9 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1854 Aug 6 (Box 2)
    - ----, [1854 Oct 15] (Box 2)
    - ----, [1854] Oct 30 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1854 Dec 9 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1857 May 27 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1857 Sep 27 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1859 Jan 1 (Box 2)
  - Chapman, Susanna (Brewitt), 1808-1892, (Mrs. John Chapman), 1868 Nov 12 (Box 2)
  - Clark, Sir Andrew, 1826-1893, 1877 Feb 1
    - ----, 1879 May 11 (Box 2)
  - Craik, George Lillie, 1798-1866, 1862 Dec 11 (Box 2)
  - Cross, Anna (Chalmers) 1813-1878, (Mrs. William Cross)
    - ----, [1871] Mar 16 (Box 2)
      Tinker 871
    - ----, [1872 Aug 19?] (Box 2)
      Tinker 872
    - ----, [1872 Sep 25] (Box 2)
      Tinker 873
    - ----, 1872 Oct 27 (Box 2)
      Tinker 874
    - ----, [1872 Nov 24] (Box 2)
    - ----, 1872 Dec 11 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1873 Jan 4 (Box 2)
      Tinker 875
    - ----, 1873 Sep 8 (Box 2)
    - ----, [1873] Sep 17 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1873 Oct 11 (Box 2)
      Tinker 876
    - ----, 1873 Dec 6 (Box 2)
      Tinker 877
    - ----, [1874] Mar 11 (Box 2)
    - ----, [1874 May 26] (Box 2)
    - ----, 1874 Jun 14 (Box 2)
      Tinker 878
    - ----, 1874 Jun 23 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1875 Sep 19 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1877 Feb 27 (Box 2)
  - Cross, Eleanor, 1847-1895, 1880 Mar 26
    - ----, [1880 Apr 13] (Box 2)
      Tinker 879
    - ----, [1880 Apr 14?] (Box 2)
    - ----, [1880] Apr 30 (Box 2)
    - ----, [1880] May 9 (Box 2)
      Tinker 880
      Addressed to Eleanor, Mary & Florence and filed under Cross, Mary
  - Cross, Emily Helen, 1848-1907 (Mrs. Francis Otter)
    - copy, [1875 Jan 13] (Box 2)
    - ----, 1880 Sep 8 (Box 2)
  - Cross, Florence Nightingale, 1857-1915 (Mrs. Henry W. Eve), 1879 Jun 17
    - ---, 1880 May 25 (Box 2)
      Tinker 881
    - ----, 1880 Aug 3 (Box 2)
  - Cross, John Walter, 1840-1924
    - ----, 1872 Dec 11 (Box 2)
    - ----, [1873 Oct 19] (Box 2)
    - ----, 1874 Jan 12 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1874 Jun 17 (Box 2)
    - Friday, [1875 Mar] (Box 2)
    - ----, 1875 Aug 14 (Box 2)
    - Envelope only, 1876 May 8 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1876 Jun 3 (Box 2)
    - Saturday, [1877 Feb 3] (Box 2)
    - ----, 1877 Nov 6 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1877 Dec 13 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1878 Apr 29 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1878 Aug 26 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1879 Jan 22 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1879 Jan 30 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1879 Feb 7 (Box 2)
    - Tuesday, [1879 Apr 22] (Box 2)
    - Thursday, [1879 Oct 16] (Box 2)
    - ----, 1879 Dec 24-25 (Box 2)
  - Cross, Mary Finlay, 1843-1902
    - ----, 1871 Jul 31 (Box 2)
      Tinker 882
    - ----, 1874 May 11 (Box 2)
      Tinker 883
    - ----, 1879 Oct 29 (Box 2)
      Tinker 884
    - ----, 1880 Jan 21 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1880 Jan 25 (Box 2)
    - ----, [1880] May 13 (Box 2)
      Tinker 885
    - Addressed also to Eleanor & Florence Cross, 1880 Jun 13 (Box 2)
      Tinker 886
    - Wednesday, [1880 Nov 17] (Box 2)
    - ----, 1880 Nov 23 (Box 2)
  - Cross, William, 1838-1916, 1880 Sep 18 (Box 2)
  - D'Albert-Durade, Alexandre Louis François, 1804-1886
    - 3 ALS and 27 MS copies by M., 1860 Jan 28 (Box 2)
    - D'Albert-Durade, 1860 Feb 7 (Box 2)
      Tinker 887, Tinker 888
    - ----, 1860 Jun 7 (Box 2)
      Tinker 889
    - ----, 1860 Jun 28 (Box 2)
      Tinker 890
    - ----, 1860 Sep 18 (Box 2)
      Tinker 891
    - ----, 1861 Jun 15 (Box 2)
      Tinker 892
    - ----, 1861 Aug 26 (Box 2)
      Tinker 893
    - ALS, 1862 Jan 2 (Box 2)
    - ----, 1862 Jul 5 (Box 2)
      Tinker 894
    - ----, 1862 Nov 28 (Box 2)
      Tinker 895
    - ----, 1863 Nov 28 (Box 2)
      Tinker 896
    - ----, 1864 Jun 24 (Box 2)